Guide to the University of Chicago Contemporary Chamber Players Records 1958-2002
University of Chicago Library
University of Chicago. Contemporary Chamber Players. Records
1958-2002
47 linear feet (57 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The Contemporary Chamber Players, a music collective based at University of Chicago, was founded in 1964 by Ralph Shapey (1921-2002), a composer and member of the university's Department of Music. The Contemporary Chamber Players performed new works by 20th century composers, and under Shapey's guidance became one of the nation's premier ensembles for contemporary art music. This collection includes the ensemble's correspondence, financial records, touring information, publicity material, performance information, and audio recordings of performances.
Information on Use
Access
Material in Boxes 55 and 56 (Series XV) is restricted for 50 years from the date of creation. Material in Box 57 (Series XV) is restricted for 80 years from the date of creation.
The remainder of the collection is open for research, with no restrictions.
Historical Note
The Contemporary Chamber Players was an art music performance ensemble founded at the University of Chicago by composer and Department of Music faculty member Ralph Shapey (1921-2002). During Shapey's tenure as conductor and director (1964-1993), the ensemble dedicated itself to the performance of compositions by the University of Chicago's doctoral candidates in composition, as well as newer or unknown composers who had not yet achieved national or international attention. Consequently, many of the composers whose works were performed by Contemporary Chamber Players went on to become prominent figures in the world of contemporary art music. Contemporary Chamber Players premiered works by composers such as Mario Davidovsky, George Perle, Shulamit Ran, George Rochberg, Roger Sessions and Ralph Shapey.
Contemporary Chamber Players benefitted greatly from funding from the Fromm Music Foundation, founded by Chicagoan Paul Fromm (1906-1987). The ensemble held an annual concert in his honor, featuring compositions by well-known contemporary art music composers. The ensemble also toured the United States, playing venues such as the Library of Congress and Carnegie Hall, as well as numerous colleges and universities. Locally, Contemporary Chamber Players worked closely with the Chicago Symphony Orchestra during the tenure of music director Jean Martinon (1963-1968).
After Ralph Shapey stepped down as Contemporary Chamber Players's director in 1993, the group was led by several resident conductors until Shulamit Ran, a faculty member and former Shapey student, became artistic director in 2002. The ensemble continues performing new art music in Chicago under the name Contempo.
Scope Note
The Contemporary Chamber Players Records includes the ensemble's correspondence, financial records, touring information, publicity material, performance information, and audio recordings of performances.
Series I: Composer Correspondence contains incoming and outgoing correspondence with composers based nationally and internationally. Correspondence with composers of note is filed alphabetically, while general composer correspondence is filed chronologically. This series spans the years 1964-1990.
Series II: Performer Correspondence includes incoming and outgoing correspondence with performers both inclusive and exclusive of the Contemporary Chamber Players ensemble. Also contained in this series are the materials sent to Contemporary Chamber Players by prospective performers, including curricula vitae, brochures and photographs. This series spans the years 1964-1991.
Series III: Performance Correspondence contains both incoming and outgoing correspondence discussing performances at the University of Chicago as well as tour performances. Related information, such as sample programs and brochures are included. Also included in this series is correspondence with the Chicago Symphony Orchestra. This series spans the years 1964-1987.
Series IV: Administrative Correspondence includes incoming and outgoing correspondence involving administrative and financial transactions both inside and outside the University of Chicago, score rental requests and invoices, and correspondence related to recordings and studio sessions. This series spans the years 1964-1990.
Series V: General Correspondence contains both incoming and outgoing correspondence with friends and benefactors of Contemporary Chamber Players, as well as general enquirers about the ensemble both within and outside of the University of Chicago. Also included is correspondence between Ralph Shapey and various staff and faculty members, friends, and general enquirers. This series spans the years 1964-1991.
Series VI: Tours contains documents pertaining to tours and tour performances, including incoming and outgoing correspondence referring to specific tour performances, tour performance notes, brochures, press clippings, personnel notes, invoices and tour budgetary information. This series spans the years 1965-1974.
Series VII: Financial, contains documents pertaining to finances and budget of Contemporary Chamber Players. Included are invoices and expense reports for Contemporary Chamber Players, as well as financial materials involving both the Fromm Music Foundation and the Chicago Symphony Orchestra. This series spans the years 1963-1987.
Series VIII: Grants and Fellowships, includes grant proposals and outgoing and incoming correspondence relating to specific grants. This series also contains documents pertaining to the Contemporary Chamber Players Fellowship Program, including grant applications, grant correspondence between applicants and recipients and the Contemporary Chamber Players, and curricula vitae. This series spans the years 1963-1990.
Series IX: Personnel, contains ensemble personnel information and documents pertaining to the Musicians' Union. This series spans the years 1964-1978.
Series X: Press and Media, includes press clippings and coverage of Contemporary
Chamber Players and Ralph Shapey, performance reviews, concert advertisements, press releases and documents and correspondence pertaining to television and radio appearances. This series spans the years 1964-2002.
Series XI: Photographs, contains photographs of Contemporary Chamber Players performers and performances, as well as photographic material used for Contemporary Chamber Players brochures and posters. This series spans 1966-2002.
Series XII: Performance and Promotion, contains materials pertaining to ensemble
performances, including promotional materials such as posters and performance programs, notes and correspondence relating to specific concert performances, instrumentation sheets, and concert and rehearsal schedules. Also included are documents related to the Lexington Quartet and Contemporary Concerts, Inc. This series spans the years 1958-2002.
Series XIII: Oversize includes all oversized Contemporary Chamber Players concert posters and photographs and one musical score. This series spans the years 1964-1982.
Series XIV: Audio, spans the years 1966-1996, and includes audio and video recordings in a variety of formats. The recordings document Contemporary Chamber Players performances, rehearsals, studio sessions, seminars and panels. The series also includes samples of work sent to Ralph Shapey by composers interested in the group.
Series XV, Restricted, contains financial and administrative records restricted for 50 years from the date of creation, and evaluative material restricted for 80 years.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Ralph Shapey. Papers
Leonard B. Meyer. Papers
University of Chicago. Seventy-fifth Anniversary. Records
Anthony Braxton. Collection
Subject Headings
Shapey, Ralph, 1921-2002; University of Chicago. Contemporary Chamber Players.; University of Chicago. Department of Music; Composers; Composition (Music); Music--20th Century
INVENTORY
- Series I: Composer Correspondence
  This series contains both incoming and outgoing correspondence with composers based nationally and internationally. Correspondence with composers of note, or with those composers with whom Contemporary Chamber Players had a close relationship, are filed alphabetically (as listed in each folder description), while the general composer correspondence and inquiries which follow are filed chronologically. This series spans the years 1964-1990.
  This series makes up the majority of composer correspondence in the collection, though some composer correspondence is included with Series VII, X and XII, interfiled with related documents.
  - Alphabetical files, 1964-1990, Allenbrook, Douglas Anderson, Ronald Ashforth, Alden Ashley, Robert Asia, Daniel Austin, Larry Babbitt, Milton Berger, Arthur Berio, Luciano Blackwood, Easley Blumenfeld, Harold Boone, Charles Braxton, Anthony Brown, Earle Cantrick, Robert Carter, Elliot (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alphabetical files, 1964-1990, Chou Wen-chung Chudacoff, Edward Cogan, Robert Copland, Aaron Cory, Eleanor Cotel, Morris Crumb, George Custer, Arthur Dallapiccola, Luigi Davidovsky, Mario Davies, Peter Maxwell del Tredici, David Deason, David Dodge, Charles Dugger, Edwin Elliott, Willard Erickson, Robert (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alphabetical files, 1964-1990, Escot, Pozzi Ekizian, Michelle Faberman, Harold Ferritto, John Foss, Lukas Franceschini, Romulus Gaburo, Kenneth (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alphabetical files, 1964-1990, Ghent, Emmanuel Hoffman, Richard Holloway, Robin Johnston, Ben Karlins, M. William Kim, Earl Kolb, Barbara Krenek, Ernst Kupferman, Meyer Lasansky, Ada Layton, Billy Jim Lawergren, Bo Lazarof, Henri (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alphabetical files, 1964-1990, Lerdahl, Fred Levine, Jeffrey Macero, Teo Mamlok, Ursula Martino, Donald Martirano, Salvatore Mekeel, Joyce (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alphabetical files, 1964-1990, Moss, Lawrence Nemiroff, Isaac Oliveros, Pauline Perkins, John Perle, George Peyton, Malcolm Phillips, Peter Powell, Mel Ran, Shulamit Rhodes, Phillip Robinson, Keith Rochberg, George Ronsheim, John Richard Salzman, Eric Schafer, R. Murray Schindler, Allan (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alphabetical files, 1964-1990, Sessions, Roger Shifrin, Seymour Shinohara, Makoto Sollberger, Harvey Stern, Robert Stravinsky, Igor Street, Tison Subotnik, Morton Suderburg, Robert Sydeman, William Talma, Louise Thorne, Francis Trimble, Lester Varese, Edgard Folder 2: Alphabetical files, 1964-1990 Varga, Balint Andras Weisgall, Hugo Weinberg, Henry Wernick, Richard Westfall, David Westergaard, Peter Wilson, George Balch Wolpe, Stefan Wuorinen, Charles Wylie, Ruth Shaw Wyner, Yehudi Yarden, Elie Zonn, Paul Martin (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chronological files, 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chronological files, 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chronological files, 1980-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series II: Performer Correspondence
  This series includes incoming and outgoing correspondence with performers both within and outside of the Contemporary Chamber Players ensemble. Also contained in this series are the materials sent to Contemporary Chamber Players by prospective performers, including curricula vitae, brochures and photographs. This series is filed chronologically, and spans the years 1964-1991.
  This series makes up the majority of performer correspondence in the collection, though some performer correspondence is included with Series VI, IX and XII, interfiled with related documents.
  - 1964-1969 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - 1980-1991 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series III: Performance Correspondence
  This series contains both incoming and outgoing correspondence discussing performances at the University of Chicago as well as tour performances. This series is divided into two subseries, and spans the years 1964-1987, and is filed chronologically.
  Subseries 1: General, includes information relating to performance inquiries and tour invitations. Related information, such as sample programs and brochures are included.
  Subseries 2: Chicago Symphony Orchestra, contains materials pertaining to performances with or including the Chicago Symphony Orchestra.
  This series makes up the majority of performer correspondence in the collection, though some correspondence referencing specific performances is included with Series VI and XII, interfiled with related documents.
  - Subseries 1: General
    - 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1969-1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2: Chicago Symphony Orchestra
    - 1964-68 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
- Series IV: Administrative Correspondence
  This series includes incoming and outgoing correspondence involving administrative and financial transactions both inside and outside the University of Chicago, score rental requests and invoices, and correspondence related to recordings and studio sessions. While the majority of the administrative correspondence is filed chronologically, there are several folders containing correspondence with specific entities. These folders are filed alphabetically by title. This series spans the years 1964-1990.
  This series makes up only part of the administrative correspondence in the collection, as administrative correspondence is also included with Series VI- XII, interfiled with related documents.
  - 1964-1969 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
  - 1980-1990 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Recording and studio sessions, 1966-1977 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Theodore Presser Co., invoices, 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series V: General Correspondence
  This series contains both incoming and outgoing correspondence with friends and benefactors of Contemporary Chamber Players, as well as with general enquirers both within and outside of the University of Chicago. Also included is correspondence between Ralph Shapey and various staff and faculty members, friends, and general enquirers. This series is filed chronologically, and spans the years 1964-1991.
  This series contains only part of the general correspondence in the collection, as general correspondence is found in Series VI-XII, interfiled with related documents.
  - 1964-1969 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1980-1991 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series VI: Tours
  This series contains documents pertaining to tours and tour performances, including incoming and outgoing correspondence referring to specific tour performances, tour performance notes, brochures, press clippings, personnel notes, invoices and tour budgetary information. Files on specific events are organized chronologically by date. General tour materials are filed in an additional chronological sequence. Also included is a file containing invoices. This series spans the years 1965-1974.
  - Concert, University of Illinois, Urbana-Champagne, March 5, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Concert, Carnegie Hall, New York, March 31, 1965- April 2, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Concert, Philadelphia Art Alliance, April 2, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Concert, Rutgers University, April 5, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Concert, Grinnell College, February 6, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Concert, Northern Illinois University, February 13, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Concert, Chicago Teachers College South, March 3, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Concert, University of Michigan, March 23, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Concert, Chicago Teachers College North, March 26, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Concert, Lake Forest College, April 28, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Concert, University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee, May 4, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Concert, Cardinal Stritch College, February 25, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Concert, Knox College, March 12, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Concert, Standard Club (Richard Gray Gallery), March 21, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Concert, Notre Dame University, April 13, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Concert, University of Iowa, April 23, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Concert, Hunter College, March 22, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Concert, Ravinia, July 2, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Eastern tour, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Concert, Library of Congress, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Chronological files, 1966-1969 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Chronological files, 1970-1974 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Tour invoices, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Series VII: Financial
  This series contains documents pertaining to finances and budget of Contemporary Chamber Players, and is separated into three subseries. This series spans the years 1963-1987.
  Subseries 1: Contemporary Chamber Players includes invoices, correspondence, and expense reports for Contemporary Chamber Players. General materials are filed chronologically, while more specific materials are filed alphabetically by folder title.
  Subseries 2: Fromm Foundation includes financial materials involving the Fromm Music Foundation, which helped fund many Contemporary Chamber Players activities.
  Subseries 3: Chicago Symphony Orchestra includes financial documents relating to Chicago Symphony Orchestra performances with which the University of Chicago was involved.
  - Subseries 1: Contemporary Chamber Players
    - Chronological files, 1963-1965 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Chronological files, 1965-1967 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Chronological files, 1970-1972 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Chronological files, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Chronological files, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Chronological files, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Chronological files, 1978-1979 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Chronological files, 1979-1980 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Chronological files, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Chronological files, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Chronological files, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Chronological files, 1983-1984 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Chronological files, 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Chronological files, 1985-1987 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Israeli Concert invoices, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Lecture invoices, 1964-1969 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - "Praise" recording and performance invoices, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Recording and broadcast financial information, 1969-1978 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Student Composers Activities Fund, 1971-1977, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 2: Fromm Foundation
    - 1970 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 1982 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 1983 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 1984 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - 1985 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 3: Chicago Symphony Orchestra
    - 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - 1967-1969 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Series VIII: Grants and Fellowships
  A brief description (ca. 50-100 words) of the material found in this series. Include after each series heading.
  - Subseries 1: Grants and Fellowships Received
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1963-1965 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1968-1970, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Ford Grant, 1970-1976 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - New York State Council of the Arts Grant, 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - National Endowment for the Arts Grant, 1974-1980 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Illinois Arts Council Grant, 1979-1989 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Art Midwest Grant, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 2: Contemporary Chamber Players Fellowship Program
    - Contemporary Chamber Players Fellowship inquiries and recruitment, 1964-1965 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Series IX: Personnel
  This series contains Contemporary Chamber Players personnel information. Included are documents pertaining to the Musicians' Union, as well as performer lists and biographical information.
  Additional materials related to Contemporary Chamber Players personnel and ensemble invoices are found in Series II, VII and XII.
  - Union documents and press clippings, 1964-1967 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Personnel Lists and Biographical Materials, 1964-1978 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Blank Personnel Contracts, circa 1965 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Series X: Press and Media
  This series includes press clippings and other media coverage of the Contemporary Chamber Players and Ralph Shapey, Easley Blackwood, and the Chicago Symphony Orchestra. Included are newspaper performance reviews, Contemporary Chamber Players press releases, and documents and correspondence pertaining to television and radio appearances. Also included are reviews and clippings unrelated to Contemporary Chamber Players. This series spans the years 1964-2002.
  - General press coverage, 1964-1986, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Chicago Symphony Orchestra press coverage, 1964-1966 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Easley Blackwood press coverage, 1964-1969 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Non-Contemporary Chamber Players press coverage and reviews, 1967-1970, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Press releases, 1964-1965, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Press Releases, 1974-1978 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Press Releases and Promotion, 2001-2002 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Reviews, 1965-66 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Reviews, 1966-67 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Reviews, 1967-68 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Reviews, 1968-69 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Reviews, 1969-70, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Reviews, 1975-1978 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Reviews, 1993-1994 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Reviews, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Radio and television, 1964-1966 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Radio and television, 1967-1969 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Radio and television, 1970-1986, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
- Series XI: Photographs
  This series contains photographs of Contemporary Chamber Players performers and performances, as well as photographic material used for Contemporary Chamber Players brochures and posters. Also included are photographs of Chicago Symphony Orchestra performances.
  Additional promotional performer photographs are found in Series II, while oversize photographs are found in Series XIII. This series spans 1966-2002.
  - Photographs, 1965-1967, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Photographs, 1967, undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Chicago Symphony Orchestra photographs, 1966-1967 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - "The Brute" performance photographs, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Lexington Quartet photographs, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Photograph – eighth blackbird, 2002 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Photographs used for copy, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Series XII: Performance and Promotion
  This series contains materials pertaining to Contemporary Chamber Players performances and the promotion of those performances. It is divided into two subseries, and spans the years 1958-2002.
  Subseries 1: Promotional Materials, includes materials Contemporary Chamber Players used for concert promotion, such as posters, performance programs, brochures and mailers, as well as source material utilized for program notes.
  Subseries 2: Performance Information contains master lists of performances, notes and correspondence relating to specific concert performances, instrumentation sheets, and concert and rehearsal schedules. Also included are documents related to the Lexington Quartet and Contemporary Concerts, Inc.
  Additional correspondence relating to performances can be found in Series III and V, while additional documents relating to touring performances are found in Series VI.
  - Subseries 1: Promotional Materials
    - Concert posters and mailers, 1964-1969 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Concert posters and mailers, 1970-1979 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Concert posters and mailers, 1980-1989 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Concert mailing lists, 1965-1966, undated (Box 12, Folder 9)